Finding Aid for Eugene Ransom and Jeanne Bailey Ransom papers, 1914-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eugene Ransom and Jeanne Bailey Ransom Papers 1914-2001
Ransom family.
2012115 Aa 2
Eugene Ransom was director of the Wesley Foundation at the University of Michigan (1951-1968). Jeanne Bailey Ransom was a teacher, writer, and family historian. The collection consists largely of binders of materials (photographs, clippings, and other memorabilia) relating to Eugene's service with the Civilian Public Service during World War II, to his work with the Wesley Foundation, and to the couples' involvement in issues of peace and justice. In addition, the collection includes collected genealogical materials and family documents pertaining to the Bailey family.
7 linear feet in 8 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Ruth Ransom Blackburn (donor no. 10600 ) and came to the library in July 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Born May 5, 1914 in Milwaukee, Wis., Eugene Ransom received his Bachelor of Arts degree in philosophy and psychology from the University of Wisconsin, Madison (1941).
Following his graduation and with the outbreak of war, Ransom as a conscientious objector served in the Civilian Public Service first at Camp Stronach in the Manistee National Forest and then as a medical technician at the Duke University Hospital in Durham, North Carolina. In July 1943, he married Jeanne Bailey who had received her Bachelor of Science degree from the University of Wisconsin in 1942. She taught science for one year in Clintonville, Wisconsin before her marriage.
With the end of the war and his release from the CPS, Ransom went back to school to receive his bachelor of divinity degree in theology from Garrett Theological Seminary, Evanston, Ill. (1949). During this time he also served as pastor of the Wesley Chapel Methodist Church in Kenosha County, Wis. In 1949, he was appointed associate pastor of the First Methodist Church in Milwaukee, also serving as director of the local Wesley Foundation. In 1951, he came to Ann Arbor as director of the Wesley Foundation at the University of Michigan serving for seventeen years until 1968. While in Ann Arbor, Ransom received his Master of Arts degree in speech (1957). He received his Ph.D. degree in education, counseling and guidance from the University of Michigan in 1964. His doctor's dissertation dealt with the role of the campus minister in a selected group of American colleges and universities.
Ransom had other responsibilities during his years at the University of Michigan, as director of the Methodist Student Movement for the state of Michigan (1956-1960) and as president of the Association of College and University Ministers of The Methodist Church and president of the Association of Religious Counselors at the University of Michigan. In 1968, he and his wife Jeanne Bailey Ransom left Ann Arbor for Nashville, Tennessee with his appointment as director of the Department of Campus Ministry of the United Methodist Church. He retired in 1979. The couple moved to Adrian, Michigan where he served as chaplain and instructor of social ethics at Adrian College. In 1985, the couple returned to Ann Arbor. Eugene Ransom died December 27, 2001. Jeanne Bailey Ransom died June 27, 2011.
As a pastor, Eugene and Jeanne were both concerned with social issues, especially peace and justice, racial equality, women's and gay rights.
The Eugene Ransom and Eleanor Jeanne Bailey Ransom papers have been carefully arranged and maintained probably by Jeanne Ransom who had an interest in genealogy and family history. The collection consists largely of binders of materials (photographs, clippings, and other memorabilia) arranged chronologically. The binders either relate to Eugene or Jeanne alone or to their activities together. Of interest are those materials relating to Eugene's service with the Civilian Public Service during World War II, to his work with the Wesley Foundation, and to the couples' involvement in issues of peace and justice. The collection also includes autobiographical material, sermons, writings, scattered correspondence, and subject files. In addition, the collection documents the Bailey family with genealogical information and family documents. One of the letters in the collection is from Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. declining a speaking invitation.
Subjects:
Bailey family.; Ransom, Eugene A.; Ransom family.; Ransom, Jeanne Bailey, 1920-; Civilian Conservation Corps (U.S.); Civilian Public Service.; Civil rights--United States.; Clergy.; Peace--Societies, etc.; University of Wisconsin--Students.; Wesley Foundation (University of Michigan); King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968.; Ransom, Eugene A.; Ransom, Jeanne Bailey, 1920-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Eugene Ransom / Eleanor Jeanne Bailey materials
  - Early activities (ER) 1914-1937 (Box 1)
    (This binder contain photographs, clippings, and memorabilia. Subheadings in the volume include Early Years, 1914 School years, 1919-1932 Dance Band, 1931-1934 C.C.C., 1935-1936 and Allis Chalmers, 1936-1937)
  - Early activities (EJB) 1920-1938 (Box 1)
    (This binder contains photographs and memorabilia. Subheadings in the volume include Early years, 1920-1925 School years, 1925-1938)
  - Gene and Jeanne Ransom -- University of Wisconsin and war years 1937-1943 (Box 1)
    (This binder contains clippings, photographs, and memorabilia. Subheadings in the volume include University of Wisconsin, 1937-1942 Camp Stronach (Gene), 1941-1942 and Clintonville, Wisconsin (Jeanne), 1942-1943)
  - Gene and Jeanne Ransom 1943-1946 (Box 1)
    (This binder contains photographs, biographical narrative, letters, and other memorabilia; Subheadings in the volume include: Wedding, July 10, 1943 Asheville, North Carolina, 1942-1944 Durham, North Carolina, 1944-1946)
  - Gene and Jeanne Ransom 1946-1951 (Box 1)
    (This binder contain photographs, programs, and memorabilia. Subheadings in the volume include Summer, 1946 Pleasant Prairie, 1946-1949 Garrett, 1946-1949 and Milwaukee, 1949-1951)
  - Gene and Jeanne Ransom 1951-1968 (Box 2)
    (This volume contains photographs, clippings, and memorabilia relating to the couple's years in Ann Arbor)
- Eugene Ransom
  - Professional Life (ER) 1946-2001 (Box 2)
    (This binder contains articles and news clippings, programs, distributed materials, and scattered photographs)
  - Correspondence 1948-1987 (Box 2)
    (this binder includes letters received and copies of letters sent relating to speaking invitations extended to public figures, current events, travels, career moves, etc. Included is a letter from Martin Luther King, Jr. expressing regret at being unable to accept an invitation from Ransom, 1964)
  - Writings 1941-1999 (Box 2)
    (This binder includes letters to the editor, articles in church and other publications)
  - Meditations 1940-1980, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Sermons 1946-1950, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Sermons 1952-1968, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Sermons 1976-1983, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Album of birthday cards and other greetings upon the occasion of his 86th birthday 2000 (Box 3)
  - Garrett Pledge (Box 3)
  - Other papers
    - Autobiography 1999 (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor 1985-1998 (Box 4)
    - Biographies (Box 4)
    - Campus ministry, Adrian (Box 4)
    - Memorials and memorial service, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Nashville 1968-1979 (Box 4)
    - Wesley Foundation, University of Michigan (Box 4)
    - Wesley Foundation, University of Wisconsin (Box 4)
    - Writings and sermons, miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Doctoral thesis, University of Michigan 1964 entitled "A Study of the Role of the Campus Minister in a Selected Sample of Colleges and Universities" (Box 4)
- Jeanne Ransom
  - Memories (autobiography)
    - My First Twenty-five Years 2000 (Box 4)
    - Ministry in Wisconsin 1946-1951 (Box 4)
    - Family Life in Ann Arbor 1951-1968 (Box 4)
  - Autobiographies / biographies (Box 4)
  - Poetry and other writings (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor / Washtenaw County schools and churches (Box 4)
- Bailey Family
  - Genealogical material, biographical sketches, copies of documents
    - Publication: A Genealogy of the Descendants of Richard Bailey (Box 5)
    - Isaac Dodge Bailey; Isaac Franklin Bailey (Box 5)
    - Nicholas Groves (1788-1866); Roxanna Stearns (1787-1824); Clarinda Holbrook (Box 5)
    - Groves family members (Box 5)
    - Groves descendants (Box 5)
    - Evelyn Partridge Bailey 1894-1916 (Box 6)
    - Myron Francis Bailey(1849-1934 with Roxa Groves 1852-1915 and Elvina Cadwell, 1855-1943 (Box 6)
    - Wilber Bailey
      - 1892-1916 (Ann Arbor and Salem, MI) (Box 6)
      - 1916-1960 (East Lansing, MI) (Box 6)
        (also includes Evelyn Partridge Bailey, 1916-1985)
    - Fitzsimmons Family (Box 7)
    - Francis Parker and family; Watson family; Hicking (Box 7)
    - Descendants of Thomas Fitzsimmons (Box 7)
    - Fitzsimmons: John (Mary Bateman) and Robert (Mary Layton) (Box 7)
  - Photographs of Ransom and Bailey family members, circa 1870s-1930s, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 8)